Finding aid to the Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence papers CA.MS.01032
Smith College Archives
Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence papers
1880 - 1945
1840-2008-10-07
Smith College Archives
Clarke, Elizabeth Lawerence, 1861 - 1951
CA.MS.01032
3.083 linear feet (6 containers)
Alumna. President of the Alumnae Association. Contains correspondence, diaries, journals, news clippings, photographs and publications documenting the life of Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence (Clarke), Class of 1883.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence papers were created by Elizabeth Lawrence Clarke (Class of 1883) and donated to the College Archives.
Biographical / Historical
As the first Smith alumna after whom a college dormitory was named (Lawrence House), Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence excelled in accomplishments while at Smith, and continued to be a leader in Alumnae communications after graduation.
Born November 11, 1861, Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence lived with her brothers George and Ned and her father, Amos Edward Lawrence. A Congregational minister, her father retired to Newton Center where he lived with his family; Elizabeth graduated from Newton High School in 1879. Though the reasons remain unclear, Lawrence joined Smith as a sophomore in 1880 and experienced quite a bit of homesickness her first month. On the top of one letter from her stepmother Lucy Watson Davis she wrote "1st letter after they left me at college. They had spent a week at Round Hills (Northampton), rather a mistake for me I think as I spent all my spare time with them instead of making friends- and then others were all settled when folks left me".
However, further correspondences are more reassuring. A letter from "Papa" as early as September 24th (1880) reads "Dear 'Tip'", a nod to Lawrence's college-given nickname. A particularly amusing letter from her brother Ned from Keene State arrived in early October, and reveals a fully adjusted undergraduate: "I am sorry to hear that your college life is getting so terribly dissipating-going to the theatre with Amherst students-going to masquerades-balls-and living on chocolate creams. I fear that you will set a very bad example to such model young ladies as are supposed to inhabit Northampton".
While in college at Smith, Lawrence lived in Number 23 Hubbard House and frequently attended shows at the nearby Opera House, recitals of music students, and outings to other college towns. Her older brother George attended Amherst College, which also made for an easier transition from home to college as they were able to connect quite easily. Though the students in Lawrence's day had less of a variety of classes to choose from than those of today, the students nonetheless had electives and took classes spanning the disciplines in the liberal arts tradition. According to the schedules meticulously saved in the pages of her scrapbook, Lawrence took classes in such diverse subjects as physics, German, French, Greek, Shakespeare, psychology, the Bible, geometry, and political economics. Also quite an accomplished athlete, she has the distinction of placing first in Smith College's first ever tennis tournament in the fall of 1882.
After graduating in 1883, Lawrence spent a year abroad travelling in such places as England, Germany, Denmark, Sweden, Russia, Austria, and Italy. She returned to Smith for a Masters degree in 1889 and continued to support her alma mater. She advised the school on physical education, and Lawrence House, the dormitory in her name, was so named "to recognize Elizabeth's skill in raising $100,000 to match an offer from John D. Rockefeller Sr.". From 1901 to 1912 she served as Secretary-Treasurer of the Association of College Alumnae (American Association of University Women), and was President of the Alumnae Association from 1909-1911. Because of her incredible involvement both as a student and as an active alumna, Smith President L. Clarke Seelye drafted her help in 1915 for the student life section in his Early History of Smith College.
For a time, Elizabeth lived in Williamstown, MA with her husband, Samuel F. Clarke, a professor at Williams College. Their daughter Beth graduated from Smith as a member of the class of 1916. Detailed accounts of attendance at Commencement reveal that, among the 70 commencements between 1879 and 1948, Elizabeth Lawrence was present at 56 of them, and gives full reasons for each of the 14 other absences. Indeed, a 1948 article in the Berkshire County Eagle reveals her to be the last surviving member at her 65th reunion.
Between the years of 1926 and 1931, Lawrence began wintering in Sarasota, Florida, finally making the move permanent in 1949. While in residence there, she founded the Smith College Club of Sarasota, Florida (1947), held an office in the American Association of University Women, and was secretary-treasurer of the Naples (Italy) table, which was an organization formed to aid scientific research for women. When not working, if the "charming, active, Mrs. Clarke is not working puzzles or keeping up with her reading, she can be seen during the big league training season, attending the baseball games over in Payne Park…and rooting for the Red Sox…'my home state boys'".
Before passing away in 1951 at the age of 89, Elizabeth Lawrence Clarke donated her portrait to the Smith College Art Museum in an attempt to clean out her Massachusetts home. The likeness now hangs in the Lawrence House living room to honor her memory and valuable influence on the early days of Smith College.
Related Materials
Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence, Class of 1883 on Smithepedia
(RG 22) Buildings records, 1875 - ongoing
American Association for University Women
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, diaries, journals, news clippings, photographs and publications documenting the life of Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence (Clarke), Class of 1883. Later materials were created by her daughter Elizabeth Clarke, Class of 1916, in partnership with her mother. Correspondence and journals dating past 1939 describe life during World War II, both in the United States and also abroad in Surrey, England.
Northampton (Mass.) - History -- Sources; Women college students -- Massachusetts -- Northampton; photograph albums; diaries; personal correspondence; Smith College. Alumni Association; Smith College. Lawrence House; Smith College -- Students -- Correspondence; Smith College -- Students -- Sources; Smith College -- Class of 1883
- Autograph Album, 1875-1879 (Box 1408, Folder 1)
- Citations, 1918; 1946 (Box 1408, Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1999 (Box 1408, Folder 3)
- Colloquium, 1915; undated (Box 1408, Folder 4)
- Commencement Attendance - chronology, 1879-1948 (Box 1408, Folder 5)
- Correspondence from Family, 1880-09-1880-12 (Box 1408, Folder 6)
- Correspondence from Family, 1881-01-1881-03 (Box 1408, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Family, 1881-04-1881-06 (Box 1408, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from Family, 1881-09-1881-10 (Box 1408, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Family, 1881-11-1881-12 (Box 1408, Folder 10)
- Correspondence from Family, 1883-03-1883-06 (Box 1408, Folder 11)
- Correspondence: Bowen, Julia A. (class of 1883), 1949 (Box 1408, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: Brooks, Frona M. (class of 1883), 1940 (Box 1408, Folder 13)
- Correspondence: Choate, Helen A. (class of 1904), 1950 (Box 1408, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Clarke, Samuel F., 1923 (Box 1408, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: Haskell, Louise Woodward (class of 1883) (Box 1408, Folder 16)
- Correspondence: Hawks, Emma B. (class of1892), 1949 (Box 1408, Folder 17)
- Correspondence: Lawrence, Elizabeth Crocker, 1883-1928 (Box 1408, Folder 18)
- Correspondence: Mather, Mary A. (class of 1883), 1882-03-11 (Box 1408, Folder 19)
- Correspondence: miscellaneous, 1883-1944 (Box 1408, Folder 20)
- Correspondence: L. Clark Seelye, "Early History of Smith College", 1915-1925 (Box 1408, Folder 21)
- Correspondence: Stoddard, John T., 1910 (Box 1408, Folder 22)
- Correspondence: Surrey, England, 1941 (Box 1408, Folder 23)
- Correspondence: Wilkie, Wendell L., 1940 (Box 1408, Folder 24)
- Book, Induction of (President) Harry Augustus Garfield, Williams College, 2008-10-07 (Box 1408, Folder 25)
- Daguerreotype, "Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence around age of 4", 1863 (Box 1409, Folder 26)
- Diamond Jubilee, 1941 (Box 1409, Folder 27)
- Handbook of Light Gymnastics by Lucy B. Hunt, 1882 (Box 1409, Folder 28)
- House in Sarasota, Florida, 1998 (Box 1409, Folder 29)
- "Longevity", article for the Harford Tribute, 1944 (Box 1409, Folder 30)
- "Kalendar, A Medley", 1892 (Box 1409, Folder 31)
- Marriage Certificate, 1892 (Box 1409, Folder 32)
- Pen holder and pen (Box 1409, Folder 33)
- Photographs, 1840-1920 (Box 1409, Folder 34)
- Photographs: portrait, 1949-1950 (Box 1409, Folder 35)
- Photographs: tennis, 1882 (Box 1409, Folder 36)
- Plaque in Lawrence House, 1949 (Box 1409, Folder 37)
- Silver bowl, gift dedication, 1933 (Box 1409, Folder 38)
- Speeches, 1879-1884 (Box 1409, Folder 39)
- Theses, 1883-1889 (Box 1409, Folder 40)
- Early History of Smith College: notes for "Student Life" chapter, A-C, 1915 (Box 1409, Folder 41)
- Early History of Smith College: notes for "Student Life" chapter, D-G, 1915 (Box 1409, Folder 42)
- Early History of Smith College: notes for "Student Life" chapter, M-O, 1915 (Box 1409, Folder 43)
- Early History of Smith College: notes for "Student Life" chapter, P-R, 1915 (Box 1409, Folder 44)
- Early History of Smith College: notes for "Student Life" chapter, S-Z, 1915 (Box 1409, Folder 45)
- Smith College Alumnae Association, 1914-1924 (Box 1409, Folder 46)
- Wedding Register, 1890 (Box 1409, Folder 47)
- Journal, 1880-1881 (Box 1410, Folder 48)
- Journal, 1880-1883 (Box 1410, Folder 49)
- Journal, 1882-1883 (Box 1411, Folder 50)
- Line-a-day, 1882-1921 (Box 1411, Folder 51)
- Line-a-day, 1885-1886 (Box 1411, Folder 52)
- Line-a-day, 1923-1927 (Box 1412, Folder 53)
- Journal, 1942-1951 (Box 1412, Folder 54)
- Journal, 1942-1944 (Box 1412, Folder 55)
- Journal, 1947-1951 (Box 1412, Folder 56)
- Guest Book at The Perch, 1892-1946 (Box 1412, Folder 57)
- Guest Book at the Eeyrie, 1900-1902 (Box 1412, Folder 58)
- Photo Album, 1882-1883 (Box 1412.1)